Today, I am going to talk about anger.
اليوم سأتكلم عن الغضب .
When I was 11,
عندما كان عمري 11 سنة ،
seeing some of my friends leaving the school
ومشاهدتي لبعض أصدقائي يغادرون المدرسة
because their parents could not afford textbooks
لأن آباءهم لا يمكنهم أن يتحملوا أعباء الكتب المدرسية
made me angry.
جعلني غاضباً .
When I was 27,
عندما كان عمري 27 سنة
hearing the plight of a desperate slave father
استماعي إلى محنة أب مستعبد يائس
whose daughter was about to be sold to a brothel
الذي كانت ابنته على وشك أن تباع في بيت دعارة
made me angry.
جعلني غاضباً .
At the age of 50,
عندما كان عمري 50 سنة ،
lying on the street, in a pool of blood,
ملقاً في الشارع، في بركة من الدم،
along with my own son,
جنباً إلى جنب مع إبني ،
made me angry.
جعلني غاضباً .
Dear friends, for centuries we were taught anger is bad.
أعزائي الأصدقاء ،منذ قرون تعلمنا أن الغضب سيء .
Our parents, teachers, priests --
آبَاءَنَـــا ،معلمونا ،وكهنتنا ...
everyone taught us how to control and suppress our anger.
كل واحد منهم علمنا كيف نسيطر ونقمع غضبنا .
But I ask why?
ولكنني أسأل لماذا ؟
Why can't we convert our anger for the larger good of society?
لماذا لا يمكننا تحويل غضبنا من أجل المصلحة العليا للمجتمع؟
Why can't we use our anger
لماذا لا نستخدم غضبنا
to challenge and change the evils of the world?
لنغير ونتحدى الشر الموجود بالعالم ؟
That I tried to do.
وهذا ما حاولت فعله .
Friends,
أصدقائي ،
most of the brightest ideas came to my mind out of anger.
معظم الأفكار البراقة التي فكرت بها جاءت من الغضب .
Like when I was 35 and sat in a locked-up, tiny prison.
ومثال ذلك عندما كان عمري 35 سنة وجلست في سجن صغير مقفل .
The whole night, I was angry.
كنت طوال الليل غاضباً .
But it has given birth to a new idea.
لكنها أدت إلى ولادة فكرة جديدة.
But I will come to that later on.
ولكنني سأتطرق لها لاحقاً .
Let me begin with the story of how I got a name for myself.
اسمحوا لي أن أبدأ بقصة حصولي على اسمي .
I had been a big admirer of Mahatma Gandhi since my childhood.
لقد كنت معجب كبير بالمهاتما غاندي منذ طفولتي.
Gandhi fought and lead India's freedom movement.
غاندي كافح ، وقاد حركة الحرية في الهند .
But more importantly,
ولكن الأهم من ذلك ،
he taught us how to treat the most vulnerable sections,
أنه علمنا كيف نتعامل مع الفئات الأكثر ضعفاً ،
the most deprived people, with dignity and respect.
والناس الأكثر حرماناً ، بكرامة واحترام .
And so, when India was celebrating
وهكذا، عندما كانت الهند تحتفل
Mahatma Gandhi's birth centenary in 1969 --
بالذكرى المئوية لميلاد المهاتما غاندي 1969...
at that time I was 15 --
في ذلك الوقت كان عمري 15 سنة ...
an idea came to my mind.
وخطرت فكرة على بالي .
Why can't we celebrate it differently?
لماذا لا نحتفل بها بطريقة مختلفة ؟
I knew, as perhaps many of you might know,
لقد عرفت كما يعرف ربما الكثير منكم ،
that in India, a large number of people are born in the lowest segment of caste.
بأن عدد كبير من الناس في الهند ولدوا في الطبقة الدنيا للمجتمع .
And they are treated as untouchables.
ويتم التعامل معهم كما المنبوذين.
These are the people --
هؤلاء هم الناس -
forget about allowing them to go to the temples,
بعيداً عن عدم السماح لهم بالذهاب إلى المعابد،
they cannot even go into the houses and shops of high-caste people.
إنهم لا يستطيعون حتى الذهاب إلى المنازل والمحلات التجارية الخاصة بالطبقة العليا .
So I was very impressed with the leaders of my town
لذلك كنت معجباً جداً بقادة بلدتي
who were speaking very highly against the caste system and untouchability
الذين كان يتحدثون بكل جرأة ضد النبذ والنظام الطبقي
and talking of Gandhian ideals.
ويقتدوا بالمثل العليا لغاندي .
So inspired by that, I thought, let us set an example
ولذلك ألهمت وتأثرت بهذه الأشياء ، دعونا نكون قدوة
by inviting these people to eat food cooked and served
من خلال دعوة هؤلاء الناس لتناول الطعام والطبخ لهم وخدمتهم
by the untouchable community.
من قبل هاذا المجتمع المنبوذ .
I went to some low-caste, so-called untouchable, people,
ذهبت إلى بعض هذه الطبقات المتدينة ، أو ما يسمى بالناس المنبوذة ،
tried to convince them, but it was unthinkable for them.
حاولت إقناعهم، ولكن ذلك كان لا يمكن تصوره بالنسبة لهم.
They told me, "No, no. It's not possible. It never happened."
قالوا لي: "لا، لا،هذا غير ممكن. ولم يحدث قط ".
I said, "Look at these leaders,
فقلت لهم: "انظروا إلى هؤلاء القادة،
they are so great, they are against untouchability.
إنهم عظماء جداً ، وضد سياسة الاقصاء والنبذ .
They will come. If nobody comes, we can set an example."
أنهم سوف يأتوا . إن لم يأتي أحد، يمكننا أن تكون مثالا يحتذى ".
These people thought that I was too naive.
يعتقد هؤلاء الناس أنني كنت ساذج جداً .
Finally, they were convinced.
وبالنهاية ، اقتنعوا .
My friends and I took our bicycles and invited political leaders.
فقمت أنا وأصدقائي بركوب الدراجات ودعوة القادة السياسين .
And I was so thrilled, rather, empowered
وشعرت بسعادة عارمة ، بدلاً من الشعور بالسطلة والتمكين
to see that each one of them agreed to come.
بأن أرى موافقة كل واحد منهم على القدوم .
I thought, "Great idea. We can set an example.
فكرت، "بفكرة عظيمة. يمكننا أن تكون مثالا يحتذى.
We can bring about change in the society."
يمكننا إحداث التغيير في المجتمع ".
The day has come.
وجاء هذا اليوم .
All these untouchables, three women and two men,
كل هؤلاء المنبوذين، ثلاث نساء ورجلين،
they agreed to come.
وافقوا على المجيء .
I could recall that they had used the best of their clothes.
ويمكنني أن أذكر أنهم استخدموا أفضل ملابسهم.،
They brought new utensils.
وأحضروا أدوات جديدة.
They had taken baths hundreds of times
واستحموا مئات المرات
because it was unthinkable for them to do.
لأنه كان شيء لا يمكن تصوره بالنسبة لهم للقيام به.
It was the moment of change.
وكانت لحظة التغيير.
They gathered. Food was cooked.
وتجمعوا . تم طهي الطعام.
It was 7 o'clock.
كانت الساعة السابعة .
By 8 o'clock, we kept on waiting,
ولغاية الساعة 8 كنا ما زلنا ننتظر ،
because it's not very uncommon that the leaders become late,
لأنه من المألوف بأن القادة عادهً يتأخرون ،
for an hour or so.
لمدة ساعة أو نحو ذلك.
So after 8 o'clock, we took our bicycles and went to these leaders' homes,
ولذلك بعد الساعة الثامنة ،ركبنا دراجاتنا الهوائية وذهبنا لمنازل هؤلاء القادة ،
just to remind them.
فقط لنذكرهم .
One of the leader's wives told me,
إحدى زوجات القادة قالت لي ،
"Sorry, he is having some headache, perhaps he cannot come."
"عذرا، لديه بعض الصداع، وربما لا يستطيع المجيء إليكم ".
I went to another leader
ذهبت إلى قائد آخر
and his wife told me, "Okay, you go, he will definitely join."
وزوجته قال لي،"حسناً، يمكنك الذهاب، وقال انه سينضم بالتأكيد."
So I thought that the dinner will take place,
فظننت أن العشاء سيقدم ،
though not at that large a scale.
وإن لم يكن على نطاق واسع.
I went back to the venue, which was a newly built Mahatma Gandhi Park.
فرجعت إلى غرفة اللقاء التي كانت حديقة جديدة تم بنائها للمهاتما غاندي .
It was 10 o'clock.
لقد كانت الساعة العاشرة .
None of the leaders showed up.
ولم يظهر أحد من القادة .
That made me angry.
وهذا جعلني أغضب .
I was standing, leaning against Mahatma Gandhi's statue.
كنت واقفا، أتكيء على تمثال المهاتما غاندي.
I was emotionally drained, rather exhausted.
كنت مستنفذاً عاطفياً ومتعباً إلى حد ما .
Then I sat down where the food was lying.
ثم جلست حيث كان يوضع الطعام .
I kept my emotions on hold.
حاولت كبت مشاعري وقتها .
But then, when I took the first bite,
ولكن بعدها ،عندما أكلت أول لقمة ،
I broke down in tears.
انهرت بالبكاء،
And suddenly I felt a hand on my shoulder.
وفجأة شعرت بيد تلمس كتفي .
And it was the healing, motherly touch of an untouchable woman.
وكانت لمسة شفاء ،لمسة أمومية لإمرأة من المنبوذين .
And she told me, "Kailash, why are you crying?
وقالت لي، "كايلاش، لماذا تبكي ؟
You have done your bit.
لقد إنتهيت من مضغ لقمتك .
You have eaten the food cooked by untouchables,
لقد اكلت طعاماً مطبوخاً من المنبوذين ،
which has never happened in our memory."
الذي لم يحدث أبداً في ذاكرتنا ".
She said, "You won today."
وقالت: "أنت فائز اليوم."
And my friends, she was right.
أصدقائي، لقد كانت على حق.
I came back home, a little after midnight,
رجعت إلى البيت، بعد منتصف الليل بقليل ،
shocked to see that several high-caste elderly people
صدمت لرؤية أن العديد من الطبقة العليا هم من المسنين
were sitting in my courtyard.
الذين كانوا يجلسون في الفناء .
I saw my mother and elderly women were crying
رأيت والدتي وامرأة مسنة تبكي
and they were pleading to these elderly people
وكانوا يتوسلوا لهؤلاء المسنين
because they had threatened to outcaste my whole family.
لأنهم تلقوا تهديد باستبعاد ونبذ عائلتي كلها .
And you know, outcasting the family is the biggest social punishment
وكما تعلمون فإن نبذ العائلة هو أكبر عقاب من المجتمع
one can think of.
يمكن للمرء أن يفكر به.
Somehow they agreed to punish only me, and the punishment was purification.
وبطريقة ما وافقوا على عقابي لوحدي وكان عقابي يتمثل بتطهيري وتنقيتي .
That means I had to go 600 miles away from my hometown
وهذا يعني أنه علي الذهاب 600 ميل بعيداً عن مسقط رأسي
to the River Ganges to take a holy dip.
إلى نهر الجانج لأحصل على غطسة مقدسة .
And after that, I should organize a feast for priests, 101 priests,
وبعد ذلك، يجب علي أن أنظم وليمة ل101 من الكهنة،
wash their feet and drink that water.
وأغسل أقدامهم وأشرب تلك المياه.
It was total nonsense,
كل هذا كان هراء ،
and I refused to accept that punishment.
ورفضت قبول هذا العقاب .
How did they punish me?
فكيف عاقبوني ؟
I was barred from entering into my own kitchen and my own dining room,
لقد منعت من دخول مطبخي وغرفة الطعام الخاصة بي ،
my utensils were separated.
وتم فصل الأواني الخاصة بي .
But the night when I was angry, they wanted to outcaste me.
ولكن الليلة التي كنت فيها غاضباً كان يريدون نبذي .
But I decided to outcaste the entire caste system.
ولكنني قررت استبعاد كل هذا النظام الطبقي .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
And that was possible because the beginning would have been
وكان ذلك ممكن لأن البداية كان يمكن أن تكون من خلال
to change the family name, or surname,
تغير كنيتي ،أو اسم عائلتي
because in India, most of the family names are caste names.
لأن معظم أسماء العائلات في الهند هي أسماء طبقات .
So I decided to drop my name.
ولذلك قررت التخلي عن اسمي .
And then, later on, I gave a new name to myself: Satyarthi,
وبعد ذلك ، سمّيتُ نفسي اسماً جديداً: ساتيارثي،
that means, "seeker of truth."
ومعناه ، "الباحث عن الحقيقة".
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
And that was the beginning of my transformative anger.
وكان هذا بداية الغضب المتحول .
Friends, maybe one of you can tell me,
أصدقائي ، ربما يود أحدكم ان يقول لي ،
what was I doing before becoming a children's rights activist?
ماذا كنت أفعل قبل أن أصبح ناشط في مجال حقوق الأطفال؟
Does anybody know?
هل يعرف أحدكم ؟
No.
لا .
I was an engineer, an electrical engineer.
كنت مهندساً، مهندس كهربائي.
And then I learned how the energy
وتعلمت بعد ذلك كيف أن الطاقة
of burning fire, coal,
من حرق النار، والفحم،
the nuclear blast inside the chambers,
الأنفجارت النووية داخل الدوائر
raging river currents,
تأتي من تيارات النهر،
fierce winds,
الرياح العاتية ،
could be converted into the light and lives of millions.
يمكن تحويلها إلى ضوء يخدم حياة الملايين.
I also learned how the most uncontrollable form of energy
تعلمت ايضاً كيف أن معظم أشكال الطاقة التي لا يمكن السيطرة عليها
could be harnessed for good and making society better.
يمكن تسخيرها للخير وجعل المجتمع أفضل .
So I'll come back to the story of when I was caught in the prison:
ولذا فإنني سوف أعود إلى قصة عندما تم القبض علي في السجن:
I was very happy freeing a dozen children from slavery,
كنت سعيداً جداً لتحرير 12 طفل من العبودية ،
handing them over to their parents.
وتسليمهم الى ذويهم.
I cannot explain my joy when I free a child.
لا أستطيع أن أعبّر عن سعادتي عندما احرر طفلاً .
I was so happy.
لقد كنت سعيداً جداً .
But when I was waiting for my train to come back to my hometown, Delhi,
ولكن عندما كنت أنتظر قطاري للعودة إلى مسقط رأسي، دلهي،
I saw that dozens of children were arriving;
رأيت أن عشرات الأطفال قد وصلوا ;
they were being trafficked by someone.
لقد كان يتاجر بهم من قبل أحد الأشخاص .
I stopped them, those people.
فأوقفت هؤلاء الناس .
I complained to the police.
واشتكيت للشرطة .
So the policemen, instead of helping me,
وبدلاً من أن يقوم الشرطي ،بمساعدتي ،
they threw me in this small, tiny shell, like an animal.
رموني بزنزانة صغيرة ، كالحيوان
And that was the night of anger
وكانت تلك ليلة الغضب
when one of the brightest and biggest ideas was born.
عندما ولدت واحدة من ألمع وأكبر الأفكار .
I thought that if I keep on freeing 10 children, and 50 more will join,
وفكرت أنه إذا ستمريت بتحرير 10 أطفال ، وأكثر من 50 طفل سينضموا ،
that's not done.
ولكن هذا لم يحدث .
And I believed in the power of consumers,
واعتقدت بقوة المستهلكين ،
and let me tell you that this was the first time
واسمحوا لي أن أخبركم أنها كانت المرة الأولى
when a campaign was launched by me or anywhere in the world,
التي تم فيها طلاق حملة من قبلي أو في أي مكان في العالم،
to educate and sensitize the consumers
لتثقيف وتوعية المستهلكين
to create a demand for child-labor-free rugs.
لخلق طلب لحماية الأطفال من العمل .
In Europe and America, we have been successful.
لقد نجحنا في أوروبا وأمريكا .
And it has resulted in a fall in child labor
وكانت نتيجتها إنحدار في عمالة الأطفال
in South Asian countries by 80 percent.
في بلدان جنوب آسيا بنسبة 80 في المئة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
Not only that, but this first-ever consumer's power, or consumer's campaign
ليس هذا فحسب بل إن حملة المستهلك ، أو قوة المستهلك
has grown in other countries and other industries,
نمت في بلدان أخرى وغيرها من الصناعات،
maybe chocolate, maybe apparel, maybe shoes -- it has gone beyond.
ربما الشكولاتة ، وربما الملابس ... ربما الأحذية .. ذهبت أبعد من ذلك
My anger at the age of 11,
غضبي في سن 11،
when I realized how important education is for every child,
عندما أيقنت كم التعليم مهم لكل طفل ،
I got an idea to collect used books and help the poorest children.
خطرت لدي فكرة لجمع الكتب المستعملة ومساعدة أفقر الأطفال.
I created a book bank at the age of 11.
لقد عملت بنك للكتب وأنا في عمر 11 سنة .
But I did not stop.
ولكنني لم أتوقف .
Later on, I cofounded
ولاحقاً ،أسست
the world's single largest civil society campaign for education
أكبر حملة لمجتمع مدني في العالم للتعليم
that is the Global Campaign for Education.
وهي الحملة العالمية للتعليم .
That has helped in changing the whole thinking towards education
والتي ساعدت في تغيير التفكير كله نحو التعليم
from the charity mode to the human rights mode,
وتحويله من موضوع خيري إلى حق من الحقوق ،
and that has concretely helped the reduction of out-of-school children
وهذا ساعد بشكل ملموس على الحد من نسبة الأطفال خارج المدارس
by half in the last 15 years.
بمقدار النصف في السنوات ال 15 الماضية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
My anger at the age of 27,
غضبي في سن 27،
to free that girl who was about to be sold to a brothel,
لتحرير تلك الفتاة الذي كانت على وشك أن يتم بيعها إلى بيت للدعارة،
has given me an idea
خلقت لدي فكرة
to go for a new strategy of raid and rescue,
للذهاب لاستراتيجية جديدة من الهجوم والإنقاذ،
freeing children from slavery.
وهي تحرير الأطفال من العبودية.
And I am so lucky and proud to say that it is not one or 10 or 20,
وأنا محظوظ وفخور بأن أقول بانهم ليسوا طفل او 10 أو 20 ،
but my colleagues and I have been able to physically liberate 83,000 child slaves
ولكن أنا وزملائي قمنا بتحرير 83,000 طفل من العبودية
and hand them over back to their families and mothers.
وتسليمهما إلى إلى أسرهم وأمهاتم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
I knew that we needed global policies.
كنت أعرف أننا بحاجة لسياسات عالمية.
We organized the worldwide marches against child labor
لذلك نظمنا مسيرات في جميع أنحاء العالم لمكافحة عمل الأطفال
and that has also resulted in a new international convention
والذي أدى أيضاً إلى ظهور اتفاقية دولية جديدة
to protect the children who are in the worst forms.
لحماية الأطفال الذين هم في أسوأ حالاتهم .
And the concrete result was that the number of child laborers globally
وكانت النتيجة الملموسة أن عدد الأطفال العاملين في العالم
has gone down by one third in the last 15 years.
قد انخفض بمقدار الثلث في السنوات ال 15 الماضية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
So, in each case,
لذلك، فإن كل حالة من هذه الحالات ،
it began from anger,
بدأت من الغضب،
turned into an idea,
وتحولت إلى فكرة ،
and action.
وفعل
So anger, what next?
أذا ما الذي يأتي بعد الغضب ؟
Idea, and --
فكرة ، ثم ماذا ....
Audience: Action
الجمهور :الفعل
Kailash Satyarthi: Anger, idea, action. Which I tried to do.
كايلاش ساتيارثي: غضب، فكرة، وعمل. هذا ما حاولت فعله :
Anger is a power, anger is an energy,
الغضب هو القوة، الغضب هو طاقة ،
and the law of nature is that energy
وقانون الطبيعة هو أن الطاقة
can never be created and never be vanished, can never be destroyed.
لا يمكن أبداً إنشائها ، ولا يمكن أن تختفي ولا يمكن أن تدمر .
So why can't the energy of anger be translated and harnessed
لماذا لا يتم ترجمة الطاقة وتسخيرها
to create a better and beautiful world, a more just and equitable world?
لخلق عالم أفضل وجميل ، عالم أكثر عدلاً وإنصافاً؟
Anger is within each one of you,
الغضب موجود بداخل كل واحد منكم ،
and I will share a secret for a few seconds:
وسأقول لكم سراً في بضع ثواني :
that if we are confined in the narrow shells of egos,
اذا بقينا محصورين في أماكن ضيقة من الغرور ،
and the circles of selfishness,
ودوائر الأنانية،
then the anger will turn out to be hatred, violence, revenge, destruction.
سوف يتحول الغضب إلى الكراهية والعنف، والانتقام، والدمار.
But if we are able to break the circles,
ولكن إذا كنا قادرين على كسر تلك الدوائر،
then the same anger could turn into a great power.
فإن نفس الغضب يمكن أن يتحول إلى قوة عظمى.
We can break the circles by using our inherent compassion
بإمكاننا أن نكسر هذه الدوائر من خلال ما نحمله من رحمة متأصلة
and connect with the world through compassion to make this world better.
والتواصل مع العالم من خلال الرحمة لجعل هذا العالم مكانا أفضل.
That same anger could be transformed into it.
نفس الغضب يمكن أن يتحول إلى ذلك .
So dear friends, sisters and brothers, again, as a Nobel Laureate,
أصدقائي الأعزاء والأخوات والإخوة، مرة أخرى، باعتباري الحائز على جائزة نوبل،
I am urging you to become angry.
أنا أحثكم أن تصبحوا غاضبين .
And the angriest among us
والأكثر غضبا بيننا
is the one who can transform his anger into idea and action.
هو الذي يمكن ان يتحول غضبه إلى الفكرة والعمل.
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
Chris Anderson: For many years, you've been an inspiration to others.
كريس أندرسون: لقد كنت لسنوات عديدة مصدر إلهام للآخرين.
Who or what inspires you and why?
من الذي ألهمك ولماذا وبماذا ألهمك ؟
KS: Good question.
كريس : سؤال جيد.
Chris, let me tell you, and that is the truth,
كريس، اسمحوا لي أن أقول لكم، وهذه هي الحقيقة،
each time when I free a child,
أنه في كل مرة عندما كنت أحرر طفلاً ،
the child who has lost all his hope that he will ever come back to his mother,
الطفل الذي فقد كل الأمل بأن يعود يوماً ما إلى أمه ،
the first smile of freedom,
الابتسامة الأولى للحرية،
and the mother who has lost all hope
والأم التي فقدت كل أمل
that the son or daughter can ever come back and sit in her lap,
أن ابنها أو ابنتها يمكن أن تأتي في يوم ما وتجلس في حضنها،
they become so emotional
أنهم يصبحون عاطفين جداً
and the first tear of joy rolls down on her cheek,
ودموع الفرح تنسال على خدها ،
I see the glimpse of God in it -- this is my biggest inspiration.
أرى لمحة إلهية في ذلك وهذا أكبر إلهام لي
And I am so lucky that not once, as I said before, but thousands of times,
وأنا محظوظ لإني لم أعمل ذلك مرة واحدة ، كما قلت من قبل ،وإنما عملته آلاف المرات،
I have been able to witness my God in the faces of those children
وقد أتيحت لي الفرصة لمشاهدة هذه اللمحة الإلهيه في وجوه هؤلاء الأطفال
and they are my biggest inspirations.
وهم أكبر الملهمات لي .
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق )